Finding Aid for Southwestern Michigan Urban League records, 1962-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Meetings 1965-2006
  - Washington Heights 1999 (Box 10)
  - Youth Advisory Committee 1970 (Box 10)
- Reports 1971-2003
  Reports (0.50 linear ft.; 1971-2003) include annual reports and reports from program managers. The reports are an effective means of gathering information about goals and accomplishments of the organization from year to year.
  - Annual Reports 1971, 1974, 1977, 1986, 1988, 1990, 1992 (Box 10)
  - Board of Directors 1972-1980 (Box 10)
  - Career Exploration 1990 (Box 10)
  - Director of Operations 1988 (Box 10)
  - Education Department 1988-1992, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Employment Department 1988-1992, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Executive Committee 1976 (Box 10)
  - Executive Director to the Board 1966-1972 (Box 10)
  - Extension Service to Albion, MI, [1972 (Box 10)
  - General Employment Procurement (Box 10)
  - Job Connection Center 1990-1991 (Box 10)
  - Mini Review and Employment Project Assessment 1980 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Reports 1991-2003 (Box 10)
  - Monthly Program Report Format (Box 10)
  - President's Report 1979, 1993-2003, 2 folders (Box 10)
- Programs 1968-2006
  Central to the collection are the records held in the Programs series and the Community Membership series. The Programs series (6.00 linear ft.; 1968-2006) contains files that document the youth and education, employment, housing and economic programs which Southwestern Michigan Urban League either sponsored or in which the organization played a significant administrative role. Well documented are the League's efforts to provide employment for both area youth and adults; job training for the unskilled and school drop-outs; educational enrichment through liaisons with high schools and the local community college, mentoring and tutoring programs; and assistance to minority owned businesses.
  - Education/Youth Programs
    - Board for Fundamental Education 1968-1969 (Box 11)
    - Community Leaders Program
      - Program Literature 1992-1996 (Box 11)
      - Participants 1994-1996 (Box 11)
      - Curriculum 1993 (Box 11)
      - Budgets 1995-1996 (Box 11)
      - Meeting Materials 1993-1996 (Box 11)
      - Newsletter, "Sistahs I've Been Thinking," 1994-1995 (Box 11)
      - Memos 1993-1996, 4 folders (Box 11)
      - Correspondence 1993-1997 (Box 11)
      - Reports 1993-1996 (Box 11)
      - Retreats 1994 (Box 11)
      - Banquet 1996 (Box 11)
      - Miscellany 1993-1996 (Box 11)
    - Cool People Community Savers 1995-1999 (Box 11)
    - Dreams of Children
      - "I Saw the Light," "Can You Hear Me," 2002-2004 (Box 11)
      - Newsletter, "Can You Hear Me?" 2002-2004 (Box 11)
      - Urban League Brass Band 2003-2004 (Box 11)
      - Video 2003 (Box 11)
    - Education Initiative Project 1986-1990, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Education Initiative Project Reports 1986-1990 (Box 11)
    - Family Focus 2006 (Box 11)
    - Focus on Readiness in Employment (FORE)
      - Curriculum Material (Box 11)
      - Events 1988 (Box 11)
      - Financial 1987-1991 (Box 11)
      - Planning 1987-1991 (Box 11)
      - Proposals 1987-1990, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Reports 1987-1990 (Box 11)
      - Reports, Monthly 1988-1990 (Box 11)
    - Girls to Women
      - Administrative & Correspondence 1999-2005 (Box 12)
      - Program Literature 1999-2003 (Box 12)
    - Male Youth Empowerment Conference 2006 (Box 12)
    - NULITES 1994 (Box 12)
    - Scholarships
      - Applicants 2002 (Box 12)
      - Contributors 1994-2001 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence 1993-2004 (Box 12)
      - Michigan State Endowment Fund 1993-2000 (Box 12)
      - Program Manuals and Applications 1997-2001 (Box 12)
      - Recipients 1995-2003 (Box 12)
      - Scholarship Committee 1999-2003 (Box 12)
    - School and Community Relations Plan 1990 (Box 12)
    - Shadow Project 1986 (Box 12)
    - Single Parents Advantage Network 1989-1990 (Box 12)
    - Stay-In-School 1989-1990 (Box 12)
    - Teen Pregnancy Prevention
      - Forum 2000-2001 (Box 12)
      - General 1999-2000 (Box 12)
  - Employment Programs
    - Challenge IV
      - Correspondence 1986-1990 (Box 12)
      - Curriculum (Box 12)
      - Employers (Box 12)
      - Financial 1987-1989 (Box 12)
      - Planning (Box 12)
      - Proposals 1986-1990 (Box 12)
      - Publicity (Box 12)
      - Reports 1986-1990, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Community Interest Group
      - Board Rosters (Box 12)
      - Correspondence 1983-1988 (Box 12)
      - Employers (Box 12)
      - Planning (Box 12)
      - Policy Board Minutes
        - 1982, 1984-1985, 3 folders (Box 12)
        - 1986-1989, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Press Releases/Public Relations (Box 13)
      - Proposals 1983-1987, 1989, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Recognition Breakfast 1982 (Box 13)
      - Reports 1984-1989, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Youth Employment Forum 1984 (Box 13)
    - Comprehensive Employment and Training Acts (CETA)
      - Contracts 1975, 1977, 1979-1981, 8 folders (Box 13)
      - Correspondence, Incoming 1979-1981, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Correspondence, Internal 1980-1981 (Box 13)
      - Correspondence, Outgoing (Box 13)
      - Orientation (Box 13)
      - Planning 1981-1988 (Box 13)
      - Reports 1986-1988, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Summer Program to Employ Disadvantaged Youth (SPEDY) 1976-1979 (Box 13)
    - Contract Compliance 1996-2001 (Box 14)
    - Employment Opportunities 1970s (Box 14)
    - Employers Designing Gainful Employment (EDGE) 1987-1989 (Box 14)
    - Fire Fighters Exam 1983 (Box 14)
    - General Employment Procurement 1987-1990, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Job Training Plan (JTPA) 1986-1988
      - Job Training Plan/Employers 1987 (Box 14)
    - Labor Education Advancement Program (LEAP) 1969-1973, 1980, 11 folders (Box 14)
    - Linear Park
      - Contracts 1984-1987 (Box 14)
      - Correspondence 1984-1988, 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Financial 1984-1989, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Planning (Box 14)
      - Proposals 1984-1987 (Box 14)
      - Publicity (Box 14)
      - Reports 1986-1988, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Task Force Meetings 1985-1987 (Box 14)
      - Youth Employee Handout (Box 14)
    - On the Job Training 1968 (Box 14)
    - Service Station Project 1969, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - STRIVE 1998-2004 (Box 15)
    - Summer Youth Employment Services 1983-1985 (Box 15)
    - Summer Employment Project 1969, 1975-1981, 1983-1985, 1988-1990, 10 folders
      - Jones, James Scrapbook 1973 (Box 15)
      - Proposals 1980-1988 (Box 15)
      - Reports 1983-1986 (Box 15)
    - Supplemental Training and Employment Program 1970-1971 (Box 15)
    - Volunteers in Service to America 1969-1971, 6 folders (Box 15)
    - Workforce Investment Act
      - General 1998 (Box 15)
      - Workforce Investment Demonstration Project 1999 (Box 15)
      - Youth Program 2001-2007 (Box 15)
    - Young Single Parents Employment 1982-1983 (Box 15)
  - General Programs
    - Block Clubs 1970, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Crisis Intervention 1980-1987 (Box 16)
    - Hypertension Program 1980-1981 (Box 16)
    - Latin American Affairs Program 1983-1986 (Box 16)
    - New Thrust 1968-1971, 12 folders (Box 16)
    - Pre-Birth to Age Three
      - Correspondence 1999 (Box 16)
      - Meetings 1999 (Box 16)
      - Program Literature 1999 (Box 16)
    - Vial of Life 1980-1981 (Box 16)
    - Weed and Seed 1999-2002 (Box 16)
    - Voter Participation Project 1971 (Box 16)
  - Housing Programs
    - Neighborhood Education and Relocation 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Neighborhoods Inc. 1993-1994, 2006 (Box 16)
    - Wilson School/Neighborhood Project 1991-2001 (Box 16)
- Community Memberships 1969-2006
  The Community Memberships series (4.00 linear ft.; 1969-2006) is particularly important for representing the role Southwestern Michigan Urban League assumed in the community after Benjamin Richmond was appointed executive director. Active participation in civic organizations became a hallmark of the League. Directors and staff were invited and/or served on boards and committees of nearly all significant organizations operating during the period and programs frequently germinated from such involvement. This series is valuable in showing the League's breadth of participation in community affairs and its interest in maintaining working relationships with other public and private social service organizations, as well as documenting the genesis of collaborative programs.
  - Access Vision 1988 (Box 16)
  - Advisory Committee on Vocational Education 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Aids Task Force 1989 (Box 16)
  - Alliance of Neighborhood Councils 1987-1989, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Battle Creek Community Foundation 1989 (Box 17)
  - Battle Creek Community Relations Council 1967 (Box 17)
  - Battle Creek Housing Commission 1967-1990, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Battle Creek Unlimited, Annual Reports 1982-1983 (Box 17)
  - Battle Creek Unlimited, Annual Reports 1986-1988, 1990-1991, 5 folders (Box 17)
  - Battle Creek Unlimited
    - May 1983-December 1984, July 1985-June 1986, January 1988-September 1988, 41 folders (Box 17)
    - October 1988-December 1989 & Miscellaneous Dates, 16 folders (Box 18)
  - Black Affairs Cultural Committee 1990 (Box 18)
  - Black Americans Cultural Council 1984-1986, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Black Business Council 1969 (Box 18)
  - Boys and Girls Club 2006 (Box 18)
  - Calhoun County Economic Development Committee 1980 (Box 18)
  - Camp Ben Johnson 1989 (Box 18)
  - Child Care Committee 1990-1991, 4 folders (Box 18)
  - Churches, Battle Creek (Box 18)
  - Cooperative Area Manpower Planning 1969-1970 (Box 18)
  - Committee for Enrichment of Human Relations 1987 (Box 18)
  - Community Action Agency of South Central Michigan 1969, 1985, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Community Chorus 1986-1987 (Box 18)
  - Community Development Advisory Council 1980, 1983-1986, 1988-1989, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Community Development Credit Union 2005-2006 (Box 18)
  - Community Groups United 1991 (Box 18)
  - Conference of Agency Executives 1967-1969 (Box 18)
  - Council of Michigan Urban League Executives, "State of Black Michigan," 1984 (Box 18)
  - Crime Prevention Program 1983-1988, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Economic Development and Employment
    - 1966-1968, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - 1970, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Greater Battle Creek Foundation 1988 (Box 19)
  - Healthy Lifestyles 1987-1989 (Box 19)
  - Hispanic Community Forum 1990 (Box 19)
  - Housing Commission 1967-1970, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Human Relations Committee 1984-1990 (Box 19)
  - Infant Health Committee 1982-1984 (Box 19)
  - Junior League 1986-1988 (Box 19)
  - Legacy Enterprises
    - African-American Leadership Summit 2002 (Box 19)
    - Rebuilding African Communities 2000-2002 (Box 19)
  - Michigan Urban League Educational Specialist (MULES) 1989 (Box 19)
  - Michigan Women's Foundation 1999-2001 (Box 19)
  - Minority Businesses 1983-1986, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs 1990 (Box 19)
  - Neighborhood Builder's Alliance 1988-1990 (Box 19)
  - Neighborhood Watch 1986 (Box 19)
  - North Central Neighborhood Council 1984-1986 (Box 19)
  - Parks and Recreation/African American Issues 1990 (Box 19)
  - Planned Parenthood 1985 (Box 19)
  - Police/Community Relations 1980, 1984-1986, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Private Industries Council 1979 (Box 19)
  - Problem Pregnancy 1986-1988 (Box 19)
  - Project Blueprint 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Sexual Assault Community Advisory Committee 1989 (Box 20)
  - Single Parents Advancement Network 1986 (Box 20)
  - Sojourner Truth Institute
    - General 1998-2000 (Box 20)
    - Publications 1997-1999 (Box 20)
  - Substance Abuse Council 1987-1991, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Summit Pointe 2006 (Box 20)
  - United Way Directors Association 1979-1980, 1989, 4 folders (Box 20)
  - United Way 1996-2004 (Box 20)
  - Voters for Community Action 1968 (Box 20)
  - Washington Community Ministries 1983-1989, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - West End Redevelopment 1984-1989, 4 folders (Box 20)
- Public Relations 1967-2001
  Researchers will find that the Public Relations series is a useful source for studying how the League portrayed itself to media and to supporters. Public Relations (.25 linear ft.; 1967-1991) includes brochures, press releases, Battle Creek area newsletters and documentation on the production of an informational video.
  - Newsletters 1967-1969, 1988-1991, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Printed Material (Box 20)
  - Press Releases 1980-1991, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Speech Material, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Speeches (Box 20)
  - Video Project 1989 (Box 20)
- Events 1966-2004
  Frequently featured in area newspapers were special affairs hosted by the Urban League or held in collaboration with other civic groups. The Events series (1.25 linear ft.; 1966-2004) documents annual events, conferences and symposiums, such as Urban League Sunday, Black Managers Forum, the Whitney Young, Jr. Annual Dinner and Black Child in Crisis.
  - "A Night to Remember" With Lou Rawls 1994 (Box 21)
  - All City Youth Talent Show 1987 (Box 21)
  - Anti-Apartheid Protest Day 1985 (Box 21)
  - Anthony McGee Tribute 1983 (Box 21)
  - Balloon Festival 1983 (Box 21)
  - Black Child in Crisis 1986 (Box 21)
  - Black History Week 1974, 1983-1984, 1988-1989 (Box 21)
  - Black Managers Forum 1990 (Box 21)
  - Board and Staff Retreat 1996, 2003 (Box 21)
  - Christmas Baskets 1985-1988 (Box 21)
  - Community Economic Development Symposium 1983 (Box 21)
  - Equal Opportunity Day 1966-1967 (Box 21)
  - Excellence in Education 1984, 1987, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Family Day 1985-2006, 4 folders (Box 21)
  - Manhood for the 90s 1989-1990, 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Martin Luther King Day 1988 (Box 21)
  - Minority Business Owner's Luncheon 1990 (Box 21)
  - National Urban League Conference
    - 1967, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 21)
    - 1993-2001, 5 folders (Box 21)
  - Network Recognition 1988-1989 (Box 21)
  - Paint Blitz 1987-1988 (Box 21)
  - Partnership Day, United Way 1989 (Box 21)
  - Prayer Breakfast 1983-1989 (Box 21)
  - Public Policy Latin American Conference 1989 (Box 21)
  - Summer Fest 1986 (Box 21)
  - Symphony Project 1984-1988 (Box 21)
  - Unity Day 1970 (Box 21)
  - Urban League Sunday 1986, 1990 (Box 21)
  - Whitney Young, Jr. Annual Dinner
    - 1967-1985, 8 folders (Box 21)
    - 1986-2004 & Miscellaneous/ Undated, 8 folders (Box 22)
- Battle Creek Area Urban League Guild 1970-2005
  The records in the Battle Creek Urban League Guild series (.75 linear ft.; 1970-2005) represent the non-programmatic community service initiatives of this all volunteer auxiliary which formed in 1970. The Guild sponsored annual and special events related to the overall mission of the League and organized fund-raising events.
  - Activities and Programs
    - Career Day Seminar 1984, 1986-1990, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Fashion Fair 1972, 1980, 1984, 1986 (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 22)
    - Mother's Day Luncheon 1996, 1999 (Box 22)
  - Administration
    - Bylaws (Box 22)
    - Correspondence 1970-1991, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Finances
      - Treasurer's Report 1982-1990, 2 folders (Box 22)
      - Proposed Budgets 1978, 1983, 1986-1990 (Box 22)
    - Minutes 1971-1990, 4 folders (Box 22)
    - Membership 1975-1999, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Procedures Manual 1996-2001 (Box 22)
  - History (Box 22)
  - Miscellany 1996, 1999, 2005 (Box 22)
  - National Council of Urban League Guilds 1993-1995 (Box 22)
- Visual Material
  The Visual Materials series consists of a collection of photographs and slides containing portraits and images of office scenes, construction sites, events. They are largely untitled and unlabeled.
  - Albums
    - Photographs and Clippings re: Urban League Guild, 1980s (Box 22)
    - Linear Park Project 1988 (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous Staff and Events 1988-1991 (Box 22)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1994-1995 (Box 22)
    - Annual Dinner 1999 (Box 23)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Dreams of Children 2004-2005 (Box 23)
    - STRIVE 1990-1998 (Box 23)
    - Urban League General 1994-2005 (Box 23)
  - Photographs, circa 1970s-1980s
    - Education and Job Training (Box 23)
    - Fashion Fair, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Joyce Brown (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
    - National Urban League Conference 1990 (Box 23)
    - Portraits, Identified (Box 23)
    - Portraits, Unidentified (Box 23)
    - Scholarship Recipients (Box 23)
    - Staff and Events 1970s-2000s (Box 23)
    - Unity Day / Other Activities (Box 23)
  - Slides: portraits, office scenes, construction sites, [1986-1988 ?], 2 folders (Box 23)
- Sound recordings
  The Sound Recordings series includes six sound tapes from late 1984 and early 1985 which are labeled "Board of Directors." Six other tapes from the same time period are titled "West End Redevelopment Association."
  - Battle Creek Area Urban League's Board of Directors September 1984-February 1985, 6 audiocassettes (Box 23)
  - West End Redevelopment Association Meetings September 1984-January 1985, 6 audiocassettes (Box 23)
- Digital Material
  Digital materials include 3.5 inch disks containing board member listings and details on the NULITES youth program. The CD-ROMs contain information on the 40th anniversary, various dream related youth programs, and newsletters. The DVDs detail reports and programs of the Kellogg Foundation.
  - 3.5 Inch Disks
    - Board Member Listings, 1 floppy disks 3.5" (Box 23)
    - NULITES, 1 floppy disks 3.5" (Box 23)
  - Compact Disks
    - 40th Anniversary, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 23)
    - Community Voices, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 23)
    - Dreams, 2 optical disks CDs (Box 23)
    - Mid-Day Magazine 2006, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 23)
    - Newsletter 2004, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 23)
    - Urban League Documents 2004, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 23)
  - DVDs
    - Kellogg Foundation
      - Annual Report 2005, 1 optical disks DVDs (Box 23)
      - From Vision to Impact, 1 optical disks DVDs (Box 23)